I hear from lots of
people every day
who are concerned about how
their diet is affecting their health.
They need answers
based on facts.
In other words,
in the peer-reviewed
medical literature,
and that is what
I’m here for.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we explore
the possibilities
of how we might have control
over our own death—
retaining dignity, privacy,
and pain relief.
And we start with a
close look at hospice.
We have all sorts
of detailed stats about dying,
but little about
the experience of death.
For the minority who die under
the care of palliative care teams
one’s death could probably
be described as good,
but there’s a suspicion that for
the majority who die in hospitals
or nursing homes
the experience is bad.
And that’s where most people die.
In spite of widespread preference
to die at home, in almost all populations,
most deaths occur in institutions.
And this doesn’t just have
consequences for the patient,
but for the bereaved caregivers
as well.
Patients with cancer who died
in an intensive care unit
or hospital experienced more
physical and emotional distress
and worse quality
of life at the end of life.
And their caregivers
suffered five times the odds
of suffering
posttraumatic stress disorder,
and nearly nine times the odds
of severe, prolonged disabling grief.
When researchers have looked into
the care of dying patients in hospitals,
it hasn’t been pretty.
Basic interventions to maintain
patients’ comfort were often not provided;
contact with dying patients
was minimal;
and the distancing and isolation
worsened as death approached.
For example, a 52-year-old woman with
metastatic cancer spread to her liver.
She had gross abdominal distension,
was jaundiced and very breathless, but alert.
Her eyes were swollen,
and she shed yellow tears.
The patient received no care
from the nurses delegated to give care.
Yet in the nursing record
it was recorded
that attention had been given
to her personal hygiene,
pressure areas to prevent bedsores,
oral hygiene, and eyes.
But it was all a lie.
The only attention she got was to receive
a commode from a nursing assistant.
Contact time totaled six minutes over
the 4.5 hours; the researchers kept track.
In contrast, what would
a good death look like?
Retaining control, dignity,
privacy, pain relief,
you choose where, you chose how,
emotional support,
respecting your wishes,
saying goodbye,
being able to leave
when it’s time to go,
and not have life prolonged
pointlessly.
One’s best bet for all that
is access to hospice care.
Palliative care is comfort measures
to relieve symptoms
and improve quality of life utilized
at any stage of a serious illness,
whereas hospice is just
comfort measures,
when focus shifts
from curing the disease
to improving the quality
of one’s last days.
Hospice is often framed
as “giving up,“ but ironically,
when you compare hospice versus
non-hospice patient survival,
the patients in hospice
actually live longer.
Patients who choose hospice care live
on average about a month longer
than similar patients
who do not choose hospice.
Randomize those with advanced
lung cancer to early palliative care,
and they don’t live a month longer—
they live two and a half months longer!
That’s like the survival benefit
you might get
from a standard
chemotherapy regimen.
And in fact, that’s one of the ways
hospice could extend survival
by avoiding the risk
of overtreatment with chemo
and its related toxicity.
There are, however,
limits to palliative care.
Even under hospice, where one would
assume excellent palliative care,
there are those who appear
to unavoidably spend
their last months
in uncontrollable pain.
And this unbearable suffering,
despite our best efforts,
leads to requests for ending
a patient`s life prematurely.
Although physician-assisted suicide
is gaining acceptance,
it’s only legal
in eight states plus D.C.
In contrast, VSED
is legal throughout the U.S.
Voluntarily Stopping Eating
and Drinking—VSED,
can be defined as a conscious
decision to voluntarily
and deliberately choose
to stop eating and drinking,
with the primary intention
of hastening death
because of the persistence
of unacceptable suffering.
I’ve talked about fasting
to extend one’s life;
what about fasting to shorten it?
We hear a lot about
physician-assisted suicide,
but VSED has not gained
nearly as much attention.
This is presented as perplexing,
since supposedly
it’s a relatively peaceful
and comfortable way to die.
But is it really?
How long does it take?
How would you do it?
I’ll talk about the pros and cons
and practical implications next.
Perhaps in an ideal world every patient
with a life-limiting illness
would receive optimal hospice
and palliative care
such that no one would ever wish
to hasten their own death.
Unfortunately, the reality
is that despite our best efforts,
some with terminal illness
continue to suffer,
leading increasing numbers of patients
across the country to explore VSED
to escape intolerable suffering,
—Voluntarily Stopping Eating and Drinking.
Some of the pros include dying at home,
which is what most people’s preference is.
You don’t have to spend
your fleeting hours
dealing with doctors and lawyers.
There is no waiting period.
In Oregon, for example,
their Death with Dignity Act
requires a 15-day waiting period before
you can get physician assistance,
whereas choosing to stop eating and drinking
would seem to afford more control.
Even just knowing it’s an option
can be a comfort.
Those who learn about VSED
may feel empowered by the knowledge
that they can choose this option
without seeking anyone’s permission,
and because it’s legal
it can be openly discussed.
Just knowing that there’s
“a way out’’
can provide relief from feelings
of desperation and entrapment.
And the feeling of control
may itself be therapeutic.
It can also prevent people from
contemplating a more violent way out,
and patients don’t have to feel pressured
to end their life prematurely
while they still can.
Physician-assisted death with dignity laws
require patients to take
the lethal drug cocktail themselves.
If you have ALS and worried about
losing your muscular function,
you might feel
the need to your end your life
before you’re ready
while you still have the capacity.
In fact, Dr. Kevorkian’s first was a woman
diagnosed with Alzheimer’s
who wanted to end it
before it got too late,
potentially depriving
her and her family
of years she might
have still been able to enjoy.
And while physician-assisted suicide entails
a single instantaneous and irrevocable act,
death from VSED occurs over several days,
allowing time for the patient
to change their mind
and for healing goodbyes.
But what is it actually like?
Ther's lots of anecdotes floating
around describing death from VSED
as peaceful, painless,
and dignified.
Fortunately, the evidence
is more than just anecdotal.
There have been several
independent studies;
so, let’s look at the data.
Average time of death after stopping eating
and drinking was about seven days,
though 8% lasted more than two weeks.
And how was it?
Ask a hundred hospice nurses
and on a scale from 0 (a very bad death)
to 9 (a very good death),
the average score–the quality
of these deaths–
as rated by the nurses, was 8.
The researchers concluded that
people usually die a “good” death
within two weeks after stopping
food and fluids,
according to the nurses rating
those last days of life as peaceful,
with low levels
of pain and suffering.
More so, even in those who chose
physician-assisted suicide.
This was in Oregon, and so,
patients could have chosen that instead,
but nearly twice as many patients
decided instead
to take matters into their own hand
by voluntarily stopping eating, and drinking.
Interestingly, loved ones seemed to agree,
with voluntary refusal of food and fluids
perceived as carrying less
"emotional baggage" for the family,
more letting go than taking
a more active approach.
A study in the Netherlands
that interviewed confidants,
like friends and family
that witnessed it,
found that most considered it
a “dignified death.”
Hospice physicians seem to agree,
with nearly 90 percent surveyed reporting
that their VSED patients experienced
peaceful and comfortable
deaths.
The state of terminal dehydration
may even have some analgesic effect,
some pain-killing effects, presumed
to be due to the release of endorphins,
which act as natural pain blockers.
So, concluded this review, VSED may reflect
all 12 principles of a ‘good death’,
retaining control, dignity...
One of the most famous accounts
was Dr. David Eddy’s description
of his own mother’s VSED:
“My mother was elated.
The next day happened
to be her 85th birthday,
which we celebrated with a party,
balloons and all.
She was beaming from ear to ear.
She had done it.
She had found the way.
She relished her last piece of chocolate,
and then stopped eating and drinking.
The last four days,
my mother greeted her visitors
with the first smiles
she had shown for months.
She energetically reminisced
about the great times she had had
and about things she was proud of.
She especially hoped I would tell
you about her traveling alone
across Africa at the age of 70,
and surviving a capsized raft
on Wyoming's Snake River at 82.
She also found
a calming self-acceptance
in describing things
of which she was not proud.
She slept between visits but woke up
brightly whenever she was touched
to share more memories and to say
a few more things she wanted us to know.
On the fifth day it was
more difficult to wake her.
When we would take her hand
she would open her eyes and smile,
but she was too drowsy
and weak to talk very much.
On the sixth day,
we could not wake her.
Her face was relaxed
in her natural smile.
She was breathing unevenly,
but peacefully.
We held her hands for another two hours,
until she died."
"Without hoarding pills,
without making me into a criminal,
without putting
a bag over her head,
and without huddling in a van
with a carbon monoxide machine,
she had found a way to bring
her life gracefully to a close.”
“Write about this, David.
Tell others how well
this worked for me.
I’d like this to be my gift.
Whether they are terminally ill,
in intractable pain,
or, like me, just knowing that
the right time has come for them,
more people might want to know
that this way exists.
And maybe more physicians
will help them find it.”
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
premiering at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.